<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
/*
 *                  Corsen development code
 *
 * This code may be freely distributed and modified under the
 * terms of the GNU General Public Licence version 2 or later. This
 * should be distributed with the code. If you do not have a copy,
 * see:
 *
 *      http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-2.0.txt
 *
 * Copyright for this code is held jointly by the microarray platform
 * of the École Normale Supérieure and the individual authors.
 * These should be listed in @author doc comments.
 *
 * For more information on the Corsen project and its aims,
 * or to join the Corsen google group, visit the home page
 * at:
 *
 *      http://transcriptome.ens.fr/corsen
 *
 */
-->
<document>

	<properties>
		<title>Corsen Application</title>
		<author email="jourdren@biologie.ens.fr">
			Laurent Jourdren
        </author>
	</properties>

	<body>
	
	      <section name="Corsen application">

		<p>The Corsen analysis is a two steps process:</p>
		<ul>
		  <li>3D segmentation</li>
		  <li>Distances computation</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Step 2 is permormed in a independent
			Java based application allowing
			distance calculation, 3D
			reconstitution and basic statistical
			analysis. Corsen application
			contains 4 tabs and requires several
			settings described bellow.</p>
	      </section>

		<section name="Launching computation">

			<p>In Corsen, the main tab is the place where informations about
				the
				current (or the last) computation is shown. The tab is composed
				of 3 parts:
			</p>

			<ul>
				<li>The files section shows the current processed files (or
					directory).</li>
				<li>The status section shows the log of the process and a
					progress bar.</li>
				<li>The execution part contains the button that launch Corsen
					processes.</li>
			</ul>


			<p>There are 4 methods to launching a Corsen computation:</p>

			<ul>
				<li>The single computation</li>
				<li>The batch mode</li>
				<li>The visualization only mode</li>
				<li>The batch mode using command line</li>
			</ul>



			<p>
				For more information about the last point, see the
				<a href="download-cli.html">command line</a>
				part of the documentation.
			</p>



			<subsection name="Launch a single computation">

				<p>
					To execute the calculation of the distances, you
					must select input
					"<b>.par</b>" files using the menus
					<b>File</b>
					/
					<b>Open particles A</b>
					et
					<b>File</b>
					/
					<b>Open
						particles B</b>
					. Then you can launch the computation by
					pressing the
					<b>Launch</b>
					button. A dialog box will appear
					to ask you the prefix of the
					outputs files. Once this step is
					fulfilled, the computation will
					run.
				</p>

				<p>While the computation, you can monitor the progress of
					Corsen with the progress bar the log on the main tab.</p>
				<p>When the calculation is completed, the results, 3D View and
					History tab will be updated.</p>

			</subsection>

			<subsection name="Use Corsen in batch mode">

				<p>
					If you want to use Corsen on several images in the aim to do
					statistical work, it will be more convenient
					to use Corsen batch
					mode. This mode requires for each particle (A and B particles) a
					set of
					"<b>.par</b>" files whose names start with de same prefix.
					Before
					launching calculation, go to the Particles tab of Corsen settings
					and define
					the prefixes of the files to be traited. Then select the
					directory
					containing these
					files
					to analyze using the menu
					<b>File</b>
					/
					<b>Open a directory</b>
					, and
					press the
					<b>launch</b>
					button to run the computation.
				</p>

				<p>As for a single computation all the tabs will be updated during
					the
					calculation progress.</p>

			</subsection>

			<subsection name="The visualization-only mode">

				<p>
					Unlike previous methods, the visualization functionality of
					Corsen
					do not compute distances between input particles but only
					show the
					3D visualization of the input particles. To launch this mode,
					follow the same steps as if you want to launch a single computation
					but press on
					<b>3D View</b>
					instead of
					<b>Launch</b>
					.
				</p>

			</subsection>

		</section>

		<section name="The result tab">

			<p>The result tab presents several data about the last couple of
				particles that has been analyzed by Corsen. Each data can be
				selected using the combobox at the top of the tab and is displayed
				in two representations: a table and a plot. Results files ("<b>.data</b>" and
				"<b>.iv</b>" output files) can be saved at this step if you didn't select
				automatic saving of output files in the settings. In the particles
				result sections of this tab, you can also save new "<b>.par</b>" files
				containing only some filtered particles (a filter can be set in the
				application settings). </p>

			<table>
				<tr>
					<th>Result to display</th>
					<th>Table description</th>
					<th>Plot description</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Data results summary</td>
					<td>Statistics informations (minimum, maximum, mean,
						median, quartiles) about minimum distances and
						maximum distances.
					</td>
					<td>Boxplot of minimum distances.</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Full data results</td>
					<td>For each center of particles B, get the intensity,
						minimal
						and maximal distances.</td>
					<td>Histogram of the distribution of minimal
						distances. The
						number of classes of the histogram can
						be set in Corsen settings.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Intensities and distances of particles B</td>
					<td>Show the intensity and volume for each particle
						B.</td>
					<td>Plot the distribution of intensity and volumes of
						particles
						B.</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Intensities and distances of preprocessed of particles B
					</td>
					<td>Show the intensity and volume for each preprocessed of
						particles B.
						</td>
					<td>Plot the distribution of intensity and volumes of
						preprocessed of
						particles B.</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Intensities and distances of particles A</td>
					<td>Show the intensity and volume for each particle
						A.</td>
					<td>Plot the distribution of intensity and volumes of
						particles
						A.</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Intensities and distances of preprocessed of particles A
					</td>
					<td>Show the intensity and volume for each preprocessed of
						particle A.</td>
					<td>Plot the distribution of intensity and volumes of
						preprocessed of
						particles A.</td>
				</tr>
			</table>



		</section>


		<section name="The 3D visualisation">

			<p>In this tab, a 3D visualization of the last A and B analyzed
				particles is displayed. For each you can select several
				visualization mode:</p>

			<ul>
				<li>No visualization</li>
				<li>Standard visualization of the particles</li>
				<li>Preprocessed particles (cuboids)</li>
			</ul>

			<p>
				In addition, two checkboxes allow the visualization of minimum
				calculated distances and particles barycenters. The last element of
				this tab is the filter view button. You can press it to open a
				dialog box that allows to filter the particles displayed in the 3D
				visualization. See the advanced topics for more information about
				<a href="advanced-topics.html">
					expression filter in 3D visualization</a>
				.
			</p>


		</section>

		<section name="The history tab">

			<p>The History tab summaries the results of previous Corsen
				computations. The table shows for each previous calculation, the
				name of the inputs file and a result from Corsen computation that
				can be selected with the combobox: mean, median, min, max of the
				distance distributions.</p>

			<p>The list of result type to display also includes an item called
				"custom". The custom statistic represents the percent of distances
				that pass a test whose expression is defined by the user in Corsen
				settings. It can be for instance the percentage of distances under a
				given threshold.</p>

			<p>On the bottom of the tab you can visualize a boxplot and a
				histogram of the table values. The plots are drawn if there are
				more than 2 values in the table. </p>

			<p>The clear button allows erasing all the results in the table
				for the next analysis.</p>

		</section>

		<section name="Corsen settings">

			<p>
				The Corsen setting is a dialog box that allow users to
				define the
				behavior of Corsen. This dialog box is available in
				<b>Settings > Configure Corsen...</b>
				menu. To keep your changes between two Corsen
				launches, use the
				<b>Settings > Save Settings</b>
				menu.
			</p>

			<p>The Corsen settings have been splited in 4 parts: Particles,
				Computation, Results and Visualization.</p>


			<subsection name="Particles">

				<p>For each particle (A and B), this tab allows to set several
					parameters:</p>

				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>The name</b>
						: Define the name of a particle.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>The type</b>
						: Define the type of a particle (see the
						<a href="advanced-topics.html">advanced topic</a>
						for more information).
						The properties button allows if available to
						set parameters
						for your
						particle type.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>The batch prefix</b>
						: Define the prefix of your "<b>.par</b>" files that is specific
						of particles in the directory to process.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>The filter</b>
						: Define a filter that will be applied on read particles. Only
						particles that
						pass the filter will be used for distance
						computation and
						visualization. (see the
						<a href="advanced-topics.html">advanced topic</a>
						for more information).
					</li>
				</ul>

				<p>In addition, you can define coordinates properties on
					particles:</p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>Z factor</b>
						: All the Z coordinates will be multiplied the defined factor.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>Coordinate factor</b>
						: All the coordinates (X, Y and Z) will be multiplied the defined
						factor.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>Unit</b>
						: Define the unit of the coordinates (e.g. pixel, µm... )
					</li>
				</ul>

			</subsection>

			<subsection name="Computation">

				<p>The Computation tab define properties on the number of thread
					to use for
					computation and the output files to generate.</p>

				<p>With no threads, the distance computation will not be
					parallelized. In automatic mode,
					the number of thread to use will be
					the number of cores/processors
					available on your computer.
					At last, the
					custom field allows you to define the desired number of threads.</p>

				<p>An option also allows to clear the result history tables
					before launching a batch.
				</p>

			</subsection>

			<subsection name="Result">

				<p>This tab allows to set the number of classes for the
					histograms in the Results and History tab.
					The other field sets an
					optional expression for the custom statistic to
					display in the
					History tab.
					The expression is a Javascript expression where <b>intensity</b> and <b>distance</b>
					are variable
					for intensity and distance.</p>

			</subsection>

			<subsection name="Visualization">

				<p>This section of the setting is about the 3d visualization
					parameters. You can:</p>
				<ul>
					<li>Set the transparency of the particles</li>
					<li>Show the negative distances in different colors</li>
					<li>Show particles A (and or B) in different colors</li>
					<li>Change the colors of all the elements of the 3D
						visualization</li>
				</ul>

			</subsection>

		</section>


	</body>
</document>
